<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Stars and Bars</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/</link><description>A blog about mathematics and computing.</description><item><title>Leveraging self similarity in problem solving</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/posts/leveraging-self-similarity-in-problem-solving</link><description>Certain problems in mathematics allow the leveraging of self similarity be reduced into far simpler problems. In this post I am going to explore one such problem...</description></item></channel><channel><title>Stars and Bars</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/</link><description>A blog about mathematics and computing.</description><item><title>The beauty of Diffie-Hellman</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/posts/the-beauty-of-diffie-hellman</link><description>Consider that you and a friend wish to communicate from a distance securely. Across the internet encryption algorithms are used to secure data that needs to be kept private such as passwords, banking details and text messages...</description></item></channel><channel><title>Stars and Bars</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/</link><description>A blog about mathematics and computing.</description><item><title>What does area have to do with gradient?</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/posts/what-does-area-have-to-do-with-gradient</link><description>The first fundamental theorem of calculus makes an interesting claim about the relationship between the area under a curve, and the anti-derivative of that curve's corresponding function...</description></item></channel><channel><title>Stars and Bars</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/</link><description>A blog about mathematics and computing.</description><item><title>Solving a hard problem by solving an easy one</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/posts/solving-a-hard-problem-by-solving-an-easy-one</link><description>For those unfamiliar, the William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition (often just called the Putnam competition) is an annual mathematics competition in the United States for undergraduate mathematics students...</description></item></channel><channel><title>Stars and Bars</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/</link><description>A blog about mathematics and computing.</description><item><title>An elegant solution to an ugly integral</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/posts/an-elegant-solution-to-an-ugly-integral</link><description>There are few problem solving challenges more satisfying than a nice integral. Integration is fundamentally built upon differentiation, as an attempt to reverse a known and algorithmic process...</description></item></channel><channel><title>Stars and Bars</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/</link><description>A blog about mathematics and computing.</description><item><title>A better approach to polynomial division</title><link>https://stars-and-bars.net/posts/a-better-approach-to-polynomial-division</link><description>Polynomials, despite being quite rare in terms of modelling real world systems, are incredibly useful in computational Mathematics, error correction codes, and to be honest, can be just a fun toy for mathematicians to study...</description></item></channel></rss>