<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Aaron Manning's Blog</title><link>blog.aaronmanning.net</link><description>A blog about mathematics and computing.</description><item><title>Exploring complex functions through animation</title><link>blog.aaronmanning.netposts/exploring-complex-functions-through-animation</link><description>It's undeniable that one of the hardest things about studying complex analysis early on is gaining a visual intuition for what complex valued functions with complex domains "look like", and how things like limits, derivatives, and integrals relate to such functions.</description><pubDate>17 March 2022</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<article style="margin-bottom: 4rem;margin-top: 3rem;"><h2 style="margin-bottom: .25rem;font-size: 2.5rem;">Exploring complex functions through animation</h2><p style="font-size: 14pt;">It's undeniable that one of the hardest things about studying complex analysis early on is gaining a visual intuition for what complex valued functions with complex domains "look like", and how things like limits, derivatives, and integrals relate to such functions. For this post, I have put together some animations to experiment with trying to provide a visual intuition for complex mappings, using the function <span class="math inline">$f(z) = z^3$</span> as an example.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This post is loosely inspired by the book "Visual Complex Analysis" by Tristan Needham.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">When typically drawing a function, the input and output spaces would be drawn independently of each other, allowing easily for drawing a total of two dimensions in the input and output space, and reasonably allowing three dimensions. However, when trying to represent a function from two-dimensional space to two-dimensional space, such as a function of complex numbers, this becomes much trickier.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">One of the most common ways of resolving this problem is by drawing a vector field. A vector field maps each input point to a vector and draws that vector with the tail at the point where the function is evaluated. By choosing to represent the complex number outputs as vectors, we can draw the function <span class="math inline">$f(z) = z^3$</span> as follows.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;"><img src="../../images/complex-cubic-vector-field.png" style="width: 100%;"></p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Notice the difference in colours between the different vectors. This is because if drawing the output vectors at their full length, it would be very hard to get any useful information due to the way they overlap. To remedy this problem, they are all drawn to the same size and colour is used to indicate magnitude, with the blue end of the colour spectrum showing shorter vectors and the red end showing longer vectors. This is quite a neat way of showing four dimensions across a two-dimensional plane, but it doesn't really give a clear understanding of what the function is doing.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Another way that a complex mapping can be represented is by showing what happens to a curve in the complex plane under the mapping. For analytic functions at least, it is generally possible to choose an appropriate curve to give a good idea as to how the function behaves off this curve. One thing that is lost in this kind of visualisation is specifically how the rate of change of the point on the path with respect to the parameter in the input space maps to the rate of change in the output space. This can be resolved through a bit of animation. Consider the animation below showing a point moving in a spiral in the input space on the left, and the cube of that point on the right-hand side.</p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o757O7r0WdM" width="100%"></iframe><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This better shows how the modulus and arguments of the complex number changes with the right point rotating around the origin faster, whilst also moving away from it faster for larger values.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This visualisation does however have the disadvantage that it only shows what happens to a very specific subset of the plane.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">So, for this next visualisation, instead of showing a point moving through the input and output space at the same time, we could animate how the path changes across one complex plane. The choice of that path will depend greatly on the function, here I have chosen to use a variety of radial lines and partial circles so that the way the angle and modulus of the complex number changes are independently obvious.</p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/e3wMnB4zymE" width="100%"></iframe><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Personally, I think this last visualisation works best. It clearly shows how the angle of the complex number is tripled, and how the modulus being cubed causes it to decrease for small values and increase for large values, depending on which side of one they sit on.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This also really helps in understanding why equations of the form <span class="math inline">$z^3 = a$</span> have <span class="math inline">$3$</span> solutions, as a full rotation of the complex plane overlaps itself three times.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">If you're interested in how the animations in this post were created, take a look at the library that I wrote which I used to create them <a href="https://github.com/aaron-jack-manning/mathil"></a>. After putting in the upfront time to developing an animation system, I plan on doing many more posts like this, so feedback on what kinds of things would be interesting is very welcome, since this post is a bit of a short proof of concept.</p></article>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Leveraging self similarity in problem solving</title><link>blog.aaronmanning.netposts/leveraging-self-similarity-in-problem-solving</link><description>Certain problems in mathematics allow the leveraging of self similarity be reduced into far simpler problems. In this post I am going to explore one such problem...</description><pubDate>20 January 2022</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<article style="margin-bottom: 4rem;margin-top: 3rem;"><h2 style="margin-bottom: .25rem;font-size: 2.5rem;">Leveraging self similarity in problem solving</h2><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Certain problems in mathematics allow the leveraging of self similarity be reduced into far simpler problems. In this post I am going to explore one such problem</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Solve the equation:</p><span class="math display">$$    x^{x^{x^{x^{\dots}}}} = 2$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">The key trick to solving this problem is noticing that because the exponentiation goes on to infinity, regardless of the chosen starting term, the expression is identical. For example, the expression shown in red below, is the same as the base expression, and is therefore equal to <span class="math inline">$2$</span>.</p><span class="math display">$$    x^{\color{red}x^{x^{x^{\dots}}}} = 2$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">It's important to note that just like in the first example of this section, this fact is only true because the number of terms is infinite.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">We can use this fact to make a substitution of <span class="math inline">$2$</span> for the top part of the expression.</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align*}        x^{2} &= 2 \\        x &= \sqrt{2}    \end{align*}$$        </span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">That was a pretty quick way to solve what seemed to be a complicated problem. Let's try using our new superpower of solving problems of this type on another problem:</p><span class="math display">$$    x^{x^{x^{x^{\dots}}}} = 4$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">First we notice the self similarity and make a substitution, so we can then solve the equation more simply.</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align*}x^{4} &= 4 \\        x &= \sqrt[\leftroot{-2}\uproot{2}4]{4} \\        &= \sqrt{2}    \end{align*}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Wait a minute, isn't that what we got for the first problem? Clearly something has gone wrong, it's impossible to take <span class="math inline">$\sqrt{2}$</span> to the power of itself, and then repeatedly take <span class="math inline">$\sqrt{2}$</span> to the power of that result, and somehow simultaneously get <span class="math inline">$2$</span> and <span class="math inline">$4$</span>. In fact, if you take any power of <span class="math inline">$2$</span> as the right hand side of the equation, you will end up with the same solution.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Since we reached a contradiction, we must have done something mathematically invalid along the way, so what could it be? There can't be an issue with our substitution because all we have done is just that, made a direct substitution. However, we have made an assumption in our work that we failed to verify. See if you can spot it before I give it away.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">By making the substitution we have assumed that there exists a solution to the equation in the first place. That there is such a value of <span class="math inline">$x$</span> that when applying this repeated exponentiation equals the right hand side of the equation. However, if no such solution exists, then everything completed from that point onward is mathematically invalid.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This is where the real fun of this problem starts, trying to explore which values of <span class="math inline">$x$</span> will converge under this process of repeated exponentiation. When trying to explore and solve a problem like this, it can be illuminating to try and find a graphical way of representing the scenario. Since we are repeatedly applying the same function, a cobweb graph seems like the appropriate choice.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">If you are not familiar with cobweb graphs, here is a simple example using a function of <span class="math inline">$f(x) = x^{\frac{3}{2}}$</span>.</p><iframe src="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/kojvfuhsbg" width="100%"></iframe><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Here the curve at the top is <span class="math inline">$y = x^{\frac{3}{2}}$</span> and the bottom line is <span class="math inline">$y = x$</span>. This graph is designed to represent what happens when repeatedly applying a function to itself. In this case we start at <span class="math inline">$x = \frac{3}{2}$</span>, and then apply our function of <span class="math inline">$f(x) = x^{\frac{3}{2}}$</span> to get an output shown where the first vertical line segment intersects our function. We then visually show the process of applying this function again by taking that <span class="math inline">$y$</span> value and using it as the <span class="math inline">$x$</span> value of our function. To do this we draw another line segment that takes us back to <span class="math inline">$y = x$</span>, and repeat the process.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Let's use the same process for the function we are using in this problem of <span class="math inline">$f(x) = a^{x}$</span>, and the starting value of <span class="math inline">$a$</span>. In the case of the graph below, <span class="math inline">$a = \frac{3}{2}$</span> is used.</p><iframe src="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/7xjn2qpcud" width="100%"></iframe><p style="font-size: 14pt;">In this case it is obvious to see that our repeated application of the function will cause it to go off to infinity. So what values of <span class="math inline">$a$</span> can we put in that will cause it to converge. Well why don't you try and figure it out for yourself by playing around with the above tool.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Notice how if you choose a small enough value for <span class="math inline">$a$</span>, the graphs intersect. When they intersect, the value of the repeated application of our function trends towards the point where the two graphs meet. So to figure out which values of <span class="math inline">$x$</span> converge, we just need to identify which values of <span class="math inline">$a$</span> give a solution to <span class="math inline">$a^{x} = x$</span>. So, let's try working with this expression to isolate <span class="math inline">$a$</span>.</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align*}a^{x} &= x \\        e^{\ln(a)x} &= x \\        \ln(a)x &= \ln(x) \\        a &= e^{\frac{\ln(x)}{x}}    \end{align*}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">If we then plot this expression for <span class="math inline">$x$</span>, we can try and see what range of values of <span class="math inline">$a$</span> are valid.</p><iframe src="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/2c5fmtq635" width="100%"></iframe><p style="font-size: 14pt;">To be expected, there is some maximum value that <span class="math inline">$a$</span> can be, which is the <span class="math inline">$y$</span> value at the turning point of our graph. So let's differentiate to find this key value.</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align*}y &= e^{\frac{\ln(x)}{x}} \\        \frac{dy}{dx} &= \frac{1 - \ln(x)}{x^{2}} \cdot e^{\frac{\ln(x)}{x}}    \end{align*}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Observe that because <span class="math inline">$e^{\frac{\ln(x)}{x}}$</span> can never equal zero, we just need to solve for when <span class="math inline">$1 - \ln(x) = 0$</span>, which yields a solution of <span class="math inline">$x = e$</span>. Substituting this back into our original expression gives <span class="math inline">$y = e^{\frac{1}{e}}$</span>, which is the maximum value of <span class="math inline">$a$</span> which can undergo the repeated exponentiation process and converge, a delightful result.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">We can now use the fact that the value of <span class="math inline">$x$</span> which gave us that maximum of <span class="math inline">$a$</span> was <span class="math inline">$e$</span>, as this will be the maximum possible value that such a process of repeated exponentiation can converge to. Since our initial equation had a right hand side of <span class="math inline">$2$</span>, which is less than <span class="math inline">$e$</span>, but the later equation which yielded the same result had a right hand side of <span class="math inline">$4$</span>, which is greater than <span class="math inline">$e$</span>, we can conclude that the answer we got of <span class="math inline">$\sqrt{2}$</span> is only valid in the first case.</p></article>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The beauty of Diffie-Hellman</title><link>blog.aaronmanning.netposts/the-beauty-of-diffie-hellman</link><description>Consider that you and a friend wish to communicate from a distance securely. Across the internet encryption algorithms are used to secure data that needs to be kept private such as passwords, banking details and text messages...</description><pubDate>4 December 2021</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<article style="margin-bottom: 4rem;margin-top: 3rem;"><h2 style="margin-bottom: .25rem;font-size: 2.5rem;">The beauty of Diffie-Hellman</h2><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Consider that you and a friend wish to communicate from a distance securely. Across the internet encryption algorithms are used to secure data that needs to be kept private such as passwords, banking details and text messages. These encryption algorithms (often) depend on a shared secret though. Let's first examine on a high level how these algorithms are used.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">To send a message to your friend, you first need to encrypt it. This encryption is done with a specific algorithm and a specific encryption key, which turns your message into scrambled data that wouldn't make any sense to someone trying to intercept it. When your friend receives the message, they decrypt it using the same algorithm and the same key, which will turn it back into readable data. Often the analogy of locking the data away in a safe is used. If you have the key, you can lock data away or pull data out.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This method of encryption is called symmetric encryption, because both the sender and receiver use the same key. Here is where the problem is: how do you share the key in the first place? Before sharing keys, you do not have an encrypted channel to share data through, and anyone listening in could just steal the key and then unscramble all future messages.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">One way to share such a key is called the Diffie-Hellman key exchange protocol, which I will describe here in such a way that it should make sense even if you have studied very little mathematics.</p><hr><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Let's first start with the ultimate goal. If you're not familiar with the relevant mathematics or computing theories, this might sound a little bit like magic, but I am going to describe a method that you and your friend could use to share a secret number, that you know, your friend knows, and no one else can find out, even if they listen to everything you say. You could yell everything to your friend across a room and no one in the room would be able to know your secret number at the end.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">You start by selecting two numbers. I will explain where these numbers will come from later in the post, for now all you need to know is that we're picking one of them to be prime (the only other positive numbers that are factors of it are one and itself) and the other to be smaller than the first. We will call these the modulus and the base respectively.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Let's say you select <span class="math inline">$23$</span> and <span class="math inline">$7$</span>. You then yell out to your friend what the numbers are. You and your friend are each now going to think of a random number of your choice, which is preferably not too small. Let's say you think of the number <span class="math inline">$7$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">You now take the base and raise it to the power of the selected number. This means we are going to multiply seven <span class="math inline">$5$</span>s together to ultimately get <span class="math inline">$78125$</span>. Now you just need to take this new number and find the remainder when dividing it by the modulus. In this case <span class="math inline">$78125$</span> divided by <span class="math inline">$23$</span> is equal to <span class="math inline">$3396$</span> with a remainder of <span class="math inline">$17$</span>. All of this is done privately without telling anyone. While you have been doing this your friend has been doing the exact same thing with their randomly chosen secret number. You can now share what you ended up with.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">You yell out <span class="math inline">$17$</span> and your friend yells out <span class="math inline">$20$</span> back to you. Now with the new number as the starting point, you do the exact same thing as you did before but with this new number as your new base. Raise it to the power of your secret number of <span class="math inline">$7$</span>, and find the remainder when dividing by the modulus of <span class="math inline">$23$</span>. This gives a result of <span class="math inline">$21$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Believe it or not, even having chosen a completely different secret number, your friend now has the same secret number at the end, being <span class="math inline">$21$</span>.</p><hr><p style="font-size: 14pt;">So why does this give the same number? Let's for a moment ignore the step where we took the remainder by division. Under this simpler protocol, all that happened was you took the base, raised it to your secret number then gave it to your friend to raise it to their secret number. From their perspective, they did the same thing. The numbers are the same because <em>the order doesn't matter when taking exponents</em>. Raising a number to the power <span class="math inline">$3$</span> and then raising it to the power of <span class="math inline">$2$</span> is the same as raising it to the power of <span class="math inline">$6$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">So what about that step where we divided by the modulus and took the remainder. Well it turns out that the exponentiation's order is independent even when we include that step. I'm not going to fully explain that in the interest of keeping this post accessible, but if you're interested in proving it for yourself, start by proving that it's true for multiplication.</p><hr><p style="font-size: 14pt;">The other cool thing about this method is that someone listening in wouldn't know what number you ended up with. Let's think about why that is. It comes down to one important fact. If I tell you I took <span class="math inline">$5$</span>, raised it to the power of a secret number, and then took the remainder of the result upon division by <span class="math inline">$23$</span>, how can you figure out what that number is? Without the division step, it's actually quite easy. If I told you I raised <span class="math inline">$2$</span> to the power of a number to get <span class="math inline">$8$</span>, it's not too hard to figure out that the number was <span class="math inline">$3$</span>. Many of you will recognise this as just calculating a logarithm. But when we take the remainder upon division by some other number, the result looks nothing like the numbers we started with, it could even be smaller than the number we started with. It turns out that the most effective way to solve this problem, is just an advanced version of trial and error. Now with numbers of the size that we chose in this example, it won't take long to guess it. However, in real world applications, very large numbers are chosen.</p><hr><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This leaves one last thing to explain. Where did those original numbers of <span class="math inline">$5$</span> and <span class="math inline">$23$</span> come from? There is one criterion I didn't mention at the time that is important, and that is that <span class="math inline">$5$</span> is what is called a primitive root modulo <span class="math inline">$23$</span>. What that means in general terms is that if you keep raising <span class="math inline">$5$</span> to different powers and taking the remainder upon division by <span class="math inline">$23$</span>, you get different results for all powers up to <span class="math inline">$22$</span>. If for example we chose <span class="math inline">$25$</span> as our modulus. Then every power of <span class="math inline">$5$</span> is divisible by <span class="math inline">$25$</span>, so we repeatedly get a remainder of <span class="math inline">$0$</span>, which we don't want. This additional criterion maximises the number of possible numbers we could get after we raise to our power and take the remainder.</p></article>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>What does area have to do with gradient?</title><link>blog.aaronmanning.netposts/what-does-area-have-to-do-with-gradient</link><description>The first fundamental theorem of calculus makes an interesting claim about the relationship between the area under a curve, and the anti-derivative of that curve's corresponding function...</description><pubDate>12 November 2021</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<article style="margin-bottom: 4rem;margin-top: 3rem;"><h2 style="margin-bottom: .25rem;font-size: 2.5rem;">What does area have to do with gradient?</h2><p style="font-size: 14pt;">The first fundamental theorem of calculus makes an interesting claim about the relationship between the area under a curve, and the anti-derivative of that curve's corresponding function. This is a relationship that is easy to take for granted. Often students are simply taught how to find an anti-derivative, and then told the fact that the difference between the value of that anti-derivative at two points gives the signed area under the initial curve. This is expressed as:</p><span class="math display">$$    \int_{a}^{b} f(x) dx = F(b) - F(a)$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">I want to explore why this is true on an intuitive level, as opposed to presenting a rigorous proof that new calculus students would learn to regurgitate. To begin, let's consider the area under the function <span class="math inline">$\sin(x)$</span> on the interval <span class="math inline">$[0, \pi]$</span>. On the plot below I have also included the anti-derivative of <span class="math inline">$\sin(x)$</span> being <span class="math inline">$-\cos(x)$</span>. Our goal here is to understand why the area shaded in red, <span class="math inline">$\int_{0}^{\pi} \sin(x)$</span>, is equal to the difference in height between the two purple points, namely <span class="math inline">$-\cos(\pi) - -\cos(0) = 2$</span></p><p style="font-size: 14pt;"><img src="../../images/ftoc1.jpg" style="width: 100%;"></p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">There are a few ways we can approach trying to find the area. One such approach is to work backwards from the average value of the function. Consider a transformation of our shaded area into a rectangle where the width is the same, but the height is equal to the average value of the function.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;"><img src="../../images/ftoc2.jpg" style="width: 100%;"></p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">The width of this rectangle is known, but then to calculate the area we'd need to know the average value of <span class="math inline">$\sin(x)$</span> across that interval. To figure this out, let's use the known relationship to the anti-derivative, since we know that's ultimately where we need to end up. Since <span class="math inline">$\sin(x)$</span> is the gradient function of <span class="math inline">$-\cos(x)$</span>, the average value of <span class="math inline">$\sin(x)$</span> is equal to the average gradient of <span class="math inline">$-\cos(x)$</span>. That average gradient across the interval is equal to the gradient of the secant across that domain, which is the difference in <span class="math inline">$y$</span> divided by the difference in <span class="math inline">$x$</span> of our purple endpoints, namely <span class="math inline">$\frac{2}{\pi}$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;"><img src="../../images/ftoc3.jpg" style="width: 100%;"></p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">When we multiply this average value of the function by the width of the interval we are examining, we get the area. Remembering that our average value was the difference in height of the anti-derivative divided by the width of the interval, we are just left with the difference in the anti-derivative, namely <span class="math inline">$\frac{2}{\pi} \times \pi = 2$</span>, because the width of the interval we are examining is divided through.</p></article>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Solving a hard problem by solving an easy one</title><link>blog.aaronmanning.netposts/solving-a-hard-problem-by-solving-an-easy-one</link><description>For those unfamiliar, the William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition (often just called the Putnam competition) is an annual mathematics competition in the United States for undergraduate mathematics students...</description><pubDate>31 October 2021</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<article style="margin-bottom: 4rem;margin-top: 3rem;"><h2 style="margin-bottom: .25rem;font-size: 2.5rem;">Solving a hard problem by solving an easy one</h2><p style="font-size: 14pt;">For those unfamiliar, the William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition (often just called the Putnam competition) is an annual mathematics competition in the United States for undergraduate mathematics students. Each year's paper contains 12 questions, each worth 10 marks. In the history of the competition, a perfect score has only been achieved 5 times and the median mark is usually zero or one point. In this post I would like to look at question B1 from the 2009 Putnam paper, as an interesting case study for how to solve a hard problem by reducing it to a simpler problem. This being question B1, it is one of the easier questions from that year's paper, and therefore hopefully not too daunting for most readers. Here's the question:</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Show that every positive rational number can be written as a quotient of products of factorials of (not necessarily distinct) primes. For example, <span class="math inline">$\frac{10}{9} = \frac{2! \cdot 5!}{3! \cdot 3! \cdot 3!}$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">The method of simplifying a complex question can be very useful within proofs. This is because sometimes complex theorems can be obtained by reaching a simpler result which implies the required result.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">The question is asking us to show that given a specific form of an expression we must comply with, there is a way of expressing every positive rational number. A question like this could be quite daunting, especially when you have no idea where to start. So let's try and simplify the question a bit.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Observe that every positive rational number is the quotient of two positive integers. Also observe that the expressions we are using are the <em>quotient</em> of products of factorials. Now due to the properties of division and multiplication, the order in which we complete these operations does not prohibit us from reaching an expression in the desired format, and therefore if we can find an expression for two given integers in the desired form, we can divide one by the other and obtain an expression for the rational number which is the first divided by the second. For example:</p><span class="math display">$$    5 = \frac{5!}{2!2!} \text{\quad and \quad} 3 = \frac{3!}{2!} \text{\quad therefore \quad} \frac{5}{3} = \frac{5!}{2!2!} \div \frac{3!}{2!} = \frac{5!}{2!3!}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Notice how by showing this implication we have allowed ourselves to solve an easier problem. By proving that every <em>positive integer</em> can be expressed as a quotient of products of factorials of primes, and using the simple result above, we can prove the required result.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Let's try our luck at simplifying the problem further by considering the constituent parts of a positive integer. Remember we are allowed to multiply and divide our prime factorials only, but using the fundamental theorem of arithmetic, we know that each positive integer can be expressed uniquely as a product of primes. For example:</p><span class="math display">$$    15 = 5 \times 3 = \frac{5!}{2!2!} \times \frac{3!}{2!} = \frac{5!3!}{2!2!2!}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">So by using the fact that every integer can be expressed as a product of primes, we only need to prove that every <em>prime number</em> can be expressed as a quotient of products of factorials of primes to prove the main theorem we need to reach.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Backtracking through our steps, we have shown the following implications:</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align*}        &\text{Every positive rational number can be written as a quotient of products of factorials of primes.} \\        \impliedby &\text{Every positive integer can be written as a quotient of products of factorials of primes.} \\        \impliedby &\text{Every prime number can be written as a quotient of products of factorials of primes.}    \end{align*}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Now let's have a crack at proving our much simpler and easier result. It might help to think of a few examples produced by trial and error.</p><span class="math display">$$    2 = 2!$$</span><span class="math display">$$    3 = \frac{3!}{2!}$$</span><span class="math display">$$    5 = \frac{5!}{3!2!2!}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">At this point, notice how with each of these, because we are producing prime numbers, we can't reach the number by multiplying smaller factors, instead we have to start with a larger number and divide through by the extra factors. One way to guarantee we're going to have a factor of the result we need, is to start with its factorial.</p><span class="math display">$$    7 = \frac{7!}{3!5!}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">You might be able to see a bit of a pattern. If you want the challenge of proving this yourself, try figuring out the next one yourself before reading on, the process of doing them will likely help you come up with a more general method.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Here is a more in depth explanation of the most recent example here. Let's start with our <span class="math inline">$11!$</span> on the top, and try and divide through by <span class="math inline">$10!$</span> to get the result we want.</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align*}        11 &= \frac{11!}{10!} \\        &= \frac{11!}{10 \times 9 \times 8 \times 7 \times 6 \times 5 \times 4 \times 3 \times 2}    \end{align*}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Notice that we can deal with the tail end and the bulk of these numbers by taking them to be the factorial of the largest prime less than 11, being 7.</p><span class="math display">$$    11 = \frac{11!}{10 \times 9 \times 8 \times 7!}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Also note that that was done without loss of generality. It doesn't matter what prime we have, we can deal with all of the numbers less than or equal to the prime below it easily. So all we need to now deal with is the composite numbers between the desired result and the prime below it. Since we're working with primes, lets try factorising them into a product of prime factors.</p><span class="math display">$$    11 = \frac{11!}{(5 \times 2) \times (3 \times 3) \times (2 \times 2 \times 2)\times 7!}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Hang on a minute, haven't we already figured all of these out though? All of our remaining numbers are numbers that we can already express as a quotient of products of factorials of primes, so we can just make a substitution, and then simplify.</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align*}        11 &= \frac{11!}{(\frac{5!}{3!2!2!} \times 2!) \times (\frac{3!}{2!} \times \frac{3!}{2!}) \times (2! \times 2! \times 2!)\times 7!} \\        &= \frac{11!}{7!5!3!}    \end{align*}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">As you can probably see, this will get out of hand very quickly, but luckily enough, we can stop here and generalise what we did for <span class="math inline">$11$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Consider the set of prime numbers in an increasing order and index to identify them <span class="math inline">$p_{0} = 2, p_{1} = 3, p_{3} = 5$</span>, etc. Consider the following expression of <span class="math inline">$p_{i}$</span> for <span class="math inline">$i > 0$</span>:</p><span class="math display">$$    p_{i} = \frac{p!}{(p - 1)(p - 2)\dots(p_{i - 1} + 1)p_{i - 1}!}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Now consider that the terms <span class="math inline">$(p - 1)(p - 2)\dots(p_{i - 1} + 1)$</span> can be expressed as a product of primes less than the prime we are trying to express <span class="math inline">$p_{i}$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Each of these primes can in turn be expressed in a similar way, with respect to primes less than themselves.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">So starting with a base case of <span class="math inline">$2$</span> where <span class="math inline">$2 = 2!$</span>, we can produce each prime in turn using the above method, and hence every prime number can be expressed as a quotient of products of factorials of primes.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Due to the fundamental theorem of arithmetic, we can express any positive integer as a product of primes, and hence the above result implies the same is true of any positive integers by simply taking the product of the expressions for each prime.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Since every positive rational number can be expressed as the quotient of two positive integers, we can apply the above result to generalise that every positive rational number can be expressed as the quotient of products of factorials of primes, the desired result.</p></article>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>An elegant solution to an ugly integral</title><link>blog.aaronmanning.netposts/an-elegant-solution-to-an-ugly-integral</link><description>There are few problem solving challenges more satisfying than a nice integral. Integration is fundamentally built upon differentiation, as an attempt to reverse a known and algorithmic process...</description><pubDate>17 October 2021</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<article style="margin-bottom: 4rem;margin-top: 3rem;"><h2 style="margin-bottom: .25rem;font-size: 2.5rem;">An elegant solution to an ugly integral</h2><blockquote style="text-align: center;font-style: italic;"><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Differentiation is mechanics, integration is art.</p></blockquote><p style="font-size: 14pt;">There are few problem solving challenges more satisfying than a nice integral. Integration is fundamentally built upon differentiation, as an attempt to reverse a known and algorithmic process. However, by the nature of that algorithm, not only are there functions which do not have an elementary derivative, there are plenty of integration challenges that can only be solved through creative thinking and pattern matching and it is my belief that the mathematics that is the most enjoyable and beautiful is that which cannot be done by a series of steps or an algorithm, but rather requires genuine insight.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">I would like to explore a problem from the 2006 MIT integration Bee.</p><span class="math display">$$    \int \sin(101x)\sin^{99}(x) \quad dx$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Now before you read on, I would encourage you to take the challenge for yourself. High school level calculus is sufficient to solve this problem, but that certainly doesn't mean it will be that level of difficulty. <strong>Spoilers follow.</strong></p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">The first thing to notice is how close our coefficient of <span class="math inline">$x$</span> inside the first <span class="math inline">$\sin$</span> is to the power of the second. Any attempt to solve this problem by conventional means with powers of trigonometric functions is going to get out of hand very quickly. An integral of this kind requires a bit of a creative trick. In fact, I will show a solution to this problem that can be written neatly and clearly with 3 lines of working.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Let's start by thinking through this problem as we would any integral by asking ourselves, what kind of expression can we differentiate to get this? One thing we can try is to get a coefficient of <span class="math inline">$100$</span>, since <span class="math inline">$101$</span> is very close to that already, and differentiating a power of <span class="math inline">$100$</span> will leave a power of <span class="math inline">$99$</span>. One way we can do that is use the trigonometric angle sum formulas, identifying that <span class="math inline">$\sin(101x) = \sin(100x + x)$</span>. Applying the corresponding identity leaves us with:</p><span class="math display">$$    \int (\sin(100x)\cos(x) + \cos(100x)\sin(x))\sin^{99}(x) \quad dx$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Just viewing the term on the right hand side, because we have <span class="math inline">$\sin(x)$</span>, distributing the <span class="math inline">$\sin^{99}(x)$</span> will give us a power of <span class="math inline">$100$</span> on one side and a power of 99 on the other. Some readers may be able to see where this is going...</p><span class="math display">$$    \int \sin(100x)\cos(x)\sin^{99}(x) + \cos(100x)\sin^{100}(x) \quad dx$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Do you see the solution yet? If you read on without trying this problem it's not too late to still try and finish it yourself!</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Maybe re-arranging the terms and putting some brackets in will make it a little more obvious?</p><span class="math display">$$    \int (\cos(x)\sin^{99}(x))\sin(100x) + \cos(100x)\sin^{100}(x) \quad dx$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">The key aspect to solving the integral from here is identifying that the derivative of <span class="math inline">$\sin^{100}(x)$</span> in the right hand term is a scalar multiple of <span class="math inline">$\cos(x)\sin^{99}(x)$</span>, and that the derivative of <span class="math inline">$\sin(100x)$</span> is the same scalar multiple of <span class="math inline">$\cos(100x)$</span> in the left hand term. So multiplying by this value:</p><span class="math display">$$    \frac{1}{100} \int (100\cos(x)\sin^{99}(x))\sin(100x) + (100\cos(100x))\sin^{100}(x) \quad dx$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Gives us an integral of the form:</p><span class="math display">$$    \int \frac{du}{dx}v + \frac{dv}{dx}u \quad dx$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">With <span class="math inline">$u = \sin^{100}(x)$</span> and <span class="math inline">$v = \sin(100x)$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Hence, the solution to our integral is:</p><span class="math display">$$    \frac{1}{100} \sin(100x) \sin^{100}(x) + C$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">A truly elegant result!</p></article>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>A better approach to polynomial division</title><link>blog.aaronmanning.netposts/a-better-approach-to-polynomial-division</link><description>Polynomials, despite being quite rare in terms of modelling real world systems, are incredibly useful in computational Mathematics, error correction codes, and to be honest, can be just a fun toy for mathematicians to study...</description><pubDate>29 September 2021</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<article style="margin-bottom: 4rem;margin-top: 3rem;"><h2 style="margin-bottom: .25rem;font-size: 2.5rem;">A better approach to polynomial division</h2><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Polynomials, despite being quite rare in terms of modelling real world systems, are incredibly useful in computational Mathematics, error correction codes, and to be honest, can be just a fun toy for mathematicians to study. Unfortunately, as a high school topic, polynomials can be quite bland and boring. When first introduced, they are a type of expression that can show up in other problems, and as such it can be handy to know how to manipulate and work with them, including through long division. The goal here being to learn how to work with polynomials as quick as possible with a thorough understanding of how it works, to then move on to the interesting bits.</p><h3>The Standard Method</h3><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Here is a common example as to how one would do polynomial division the conventional way, in this case to divide <span class="math inline">$x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2$</span> by <span class="math inline">$x^2 + 2x + 3$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">First we write our divisor out the front of our polynomial that we wish to divide, with a vinculum over it.</p><span class="math display">$$    \require{enclose}    \begin{array}{rll}        \phantom{x^4 + 2x^3 + x^2 + 0x - 3}\\[-3pt]x^2 + 2x + 3\enclose{longdiv}{x^4 + 2x^3 + 0x^2 + 3x + 2}    \end{array}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Now we ask ourselves, how many times does or polynomial go into our first term of <span class="math inline">$x^4$</span>? Well, uhhhh, <span class="math inline">$x^2$</span> times? This is what students are expected to say, and expected to write, but does this really make any sense? If you multiply <span class="math inline">$x^2$</span> by <span class="math inline">$x^2 + 2x + 3$</span> you don't get <span class="math inline">$x^4$</span> because you still have leftover terms, and this notion of a remainder is far less intuitive in the context of polynomials.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Many people choose to think of this as how many times does the first term of our divisor divide the first term of our polynomial, but can you see a clear reason why you would do that? We are trying to divide our whole divisor in, not just the first term. Let's just march on though in the way we're supposed to and see what happens.</p><span class="math display">$$    \require{enclose}    \begin{array}{rll}        \phantom{x^4 + 2x^3 +} x^2 \phantom{+ 0x - 3}\\[-3pt]x^2 + 2x + 3\enclose{longdiv}{x^4 + 2x^3 + 0x^2 + 3x + 2}    \end{array}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Now we multiply <span class="math inline">$x^2$</span> by our divisor and are left with a polynomial we then subtract from our initial polynomial, completely ignoring the tail end of the terms. Why do we do this? Why can we ignore these terms for now and write them in later? Why do we write in specifically the number of terms that we do? These are all questions with answers, but answers that are not intuitive or obvious from the way we complete the operation. I am a firm believer that mathematical notation and process should be explanatory in and of itself as much as possible.</p><span class="math display">$$    \require{enclose}    \begin{array}{rll}        \phantom{x^4 + 2x^3 +} x^2 \phantom{+ 0x - 3}\\[-3pt]x^2 + 2x + 3\enclose{longdiv}{x^4 + 2x^3 + 0x^2 + 3x + 2}\kern-.2ex \\[-3pt]\underline{-x^4 - 2x^3 - 3x^2} \phantom{+ 3x - 2}    \end{array}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">After completing the subtraction and writing down our remaining terms, we are left with the following:</p><span class="math display">$$    \require{enclose}    \begin{array}{rll}        \phantom{x^4 + 2x^3 +} x^2 \phantom{+ 0x - 3}\\[-3pt]x^2 + 2x + 3\enclose{longdiv}{x^4 + 2x^3 + 0x^2 + 3x + 2}\kern-.2ex \\[-3pt]\underline{-x^4 - 2x^3 - 3x^2} \phantom{+ 3x - 2} \\[-3pt]-3x^2 + 3x + 2    \end{array}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Which then allows us to repeat the process from before, asking how many times <span class="math inline">$x^2$</span> divides <span class="math inline">$-3x^2$</span>, and writing that up the top.</p><span class="math display">$$    \require{enclose}    \begin{array}{rll}        \phantom{x^4 + 2x^3 +} x^2 \phantom{+ 0x} - 3\\[-3pt]x^2 + 2x + 3\enclose{longdiv}{x^4 + 2x^3 + 0x^2 + 3x + 2}\kern-.2ex \\[-3pt]\underline{-x^4 - 2x^3 - 3x^2} \phantom{+ 3x - 2} \\[-3pt]-3x^2 + 3x + 2    \end{array}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">We can then subtract <span class="math inline">$-3$</span> times our divisor and we are done.</p><span class="math display">$$    \require{enclose}    \begin{array}{rll}        \phantom{x^4 + 2x^3 +} x^2 \phantom{+ 0x} - 3\\[-3pt]x^2 + 2x + 3\enclose{longdiv}{x^4 + 2x^3 + 0x^2 + 3x + 2}\kern-.2ex \\[-3pt]\underline{-x^4 - 2x^3 - 3x^2} \phantom{+ 3x - 2} \\[-3pt]-3x^2 + 3x + 2\\[-3pt]\underline{3x^2 + 6x + 9}    \end{array}$$</span><span class="math display">$$    \require{enclose}    \begin{array}{rll}        \phantom{x^4 + 2x^3 +} x^2 \phantom{+ 0x} - 3\\[-3pt]x^2 + 2x + 3\enclose{longdiv}{x^4 + 2x^3 + 0x^2 + 3x + 2}\kern-.2ex \\[-3pt]\underline{-x^4 - 2x^3 - 3x^2} \phantom{+ 3x - 2} \\[-3pt]-3x^2 + 3x + 2\\[-3pt]\underline{3x^2 + 6x + 9}\\[-3pt]9x + 11    \end{array}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This leaves the divisor on the right, our polynomial that we started with under our vinculum, the quotient over the vinculum and the remainder at the bottom. Not only is it confusing to have the quotient written over the initial polynomial, but the whole process is a series of memorised steps that don't really make mathematical sense so that we can then memorise where each part of our expression is to ultimately write it in the form we want: <span class="math inline">$P(x) = D(x)Q(x) + R(x)$</span>.</p><span class="math display">$$    (x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2) = (x^2 - 3)(x^2 + 2x + 3) + (9x + 11)$$</span><h3>A Better Approach</h3><p style="font-size: 14pt;">I now propose an alternate approach to polynomial division, which I will argue is simpler, easier to learn, more intuitive and works better within the problems that it is used. It will also provide us with the result in a nicer format and most importantly will rely on students existing intuition for how division works with numbers and how to manipulate algebraic expressions. However, we should first look at how the division algorithm works with integers, to show just how nicely the polynomial form will follow on from it.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Let's say we want to divide <span class="math inline">$45$</span> by <span class="math inline">$13$</span>. The division algorithm states that for any positive integers <span class="math inline">$a$</span> and <span class="math inline">$b$</span>, there exists a unique <span class="math inline">$q$</span> and <span class="math inline">$r$</span> with <span class="math inline">$0 \leq r < b$</span> such that:</p><span class="math display">$$    a = qb + r$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">This is just that for any choice of <span class="math inline">$a$</span>, and a  <span class="math inline">$b$</span> that we wish to divide it by, we can find a unique quotient and remainder. So for our above example, the largest multiple of <span class="math inline">$13$</span> that is still lass than <span class="math inline">$45$</span> is <span class="math inline">$3$</span>, hence:</p><span class="math display">$$    45 = 13 \cdot 3 + 6$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">We will now complete a very similar process for polynomials, with some small differences. These differences however should clearly show what is happening as the division occurs and should make sense from start to finish with respect to the underlying mathematics.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">We begin by writing out the polynomial we wish to divide on one side of an equation, and the divisor on the other, leaving space for other things we will write in. This is because ultimately we want our initial polynomial in terms of the divisor.</p><span class="math display">$$    x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2 = \phantom{x^2}(x^2 + 2x + 3) \phantom{-3x^2 + 3x + 2}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Now the process of polynomial division is just about matching algebraic terms. In order for our right hand side to be equal to our left hand side, we must make our first term <span class="math inline">$x^4$</span>. To do this we multiply by <span class="math inline">$x^4$</span>.</p><span class="math display">$$    x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2 = x^2(x^2 + 2x + 3) \phantom{-3x^2 + 3x + 2}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">So we have matched the first term for when we expand our right hand side, but we need to make sure our expressions are equal, so we add and subtract lower degree terms to compensate. For example, when we expand our right hand side we will end up with a <span class="math inline">$2x^3$</span> term, which we already have on the left hand side. So good so far. The next term we will get will be <span class="math inline">$3x^2$</span>, but that's not on the left hand side so we have to subtract it to make sure our equation holds. Similarly, we will be missing the <span class="math inline">$3x + 2$</span>, so we will also add that to the end.</p><span class="math display">$$    x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2 = x^2(x^2 + 2x + 3) -3x^2 + 3x + 2$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Now we just repeat the exact same thing for the tail end of our terms. So we can for now ignore our first term of <span class="math inline">$x^2(x^2 + 2x + 3)$</span>, and just divide <span class="math inline">$-3x^2 + 3x + 2$</span> by our divisor. In this case, we need to multiply our quotient by <span class="math inline">$-3$</span> to match our leading term, and then we can add or subtract our extra terms so our expression is still equal.</p><span class="math display">$$    x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2 = x^2(x^2 + 2x + 3) -3(x^2 + 2x + 3) + 9x + 11$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Since the degree of our remaining expression is less than our divisor, we have nothing more to divide. So let's just factorise out divisor and we are done!</p><span class="math display">$$    x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2 = (x^2 + 2x + 3)(x^2 - 3) + 9x + 11$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Now, with no further work, just as a consequence of the process, we are left with the standard form of <span class="math inline">$P(x) = D(x)Q(x) + R(x)$</span>.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">With a little bit of practice this process becomes easy, allowing your full working to look just like this:</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align}        x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2 &= x^2(x^2 + 2x + 3) - 3x^2 + 3x + 2 \\&= x^2(x^2 + 2x + 3) - 3(x^2 + 2x + 3) + 9x + 11 \\&= (x^2 + 2x + 3)(x^2 - 3) + 9x + 11    \end{align}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Not only is this method easier to learn and intuitively understand for someone being introduced to the topic, it is also better suited to the cases where polynomial division is actually used. For example, consider the use of the Euclidean Algorithm to find the greatest common divisor of two polynomials. We will use the same example as before, meaning the first few steps are already done for us.</p><span class="math display">$$    \begin{align}        x^4 + 2x^3 + 3x + 2 &= x^2(x^2 + 2x + 3) - 3x^2 + 3x + 2 \\&= x^2(x^2 + 2x + 3) - 3(x^2 + 2x + 3) + 9x + 11 \\&= (x^2 + 2x + 3)(x^2 - 3) + 9x + 11 \\x^2 + 2x + 3 &= \frac{1}{9}x(9x + 11) + \frac{7}{9}x + 3 \\&= \frac{1}{9}x(9x + 11) + \frac{7}{81}(9x + 11) + \frac{166}{81} \\&= (9x + 11)\left(\frac{1}{9}x + \frac{7}{81}\right) + \frac{166}{81} \\9x + 1 &= \frac{166}{81}\left(\frac{729}{166}x + \frac{891}{166}\right)    \end{align}$$</span><p style="font-size: 14pt;">Note how this process looks just like how it would be written for using the Euclidean Algorithm to find the greatest common denominator of two integers.</p><p style="font-size: 14pt;">My ultimate goal in writing this post is to encourage readers to further consider how mathematical methods for computations influence one's understanding of the concept itself, and more importantly to realise that some methods are easy precisely because they're familiar, and that makes it hard to identify where they could be problematic for people learning them for the first time.</p></article>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>